Guide to the Potomac Area Council American Youth Hostels records, 1943-2011 MS2196
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Scrapbooks and annotated photograph albums, 1940 ca.-1995; Series 4; 1.5 Linear Feet (Box 2, Box 3)
  - 50th anniversary displays [2/2], 1995 ca.; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Display photograph, undated; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Very Special Events, undated; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Audiotapes and film, 1956 and undated; Series 5; 0.25 Linear Feet
  This series contains two audiotapes. The first, from 1956, is an appearance by Donald Messersmith on WFAX radio in Falls Church, Va. The second tape, undated, is an oral history of AYH.
  - Audiotapes: "Don Messersmith from WFAX, Falls Church, Va. - AYH" & "AYH 50th Anniversary", 1956 May 24 - Circa 1995; Series 5 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Contains 2 audiotapes
  - Hosteling Along The Potomac, undated; Series 5 (Flat box 7, Reel 1)
    A movie taken on the three day hiking and biking trip sponsored by the AYH and Vista for Baltimore youth.
  - Sandy Hook Hostel dedication, 1962 May 5; Series 5 (Flat box 7, Reel 2)
    1:00pm 7 1/2"/sec half-track
  - 25th Anniversary Banquet Potomac Area Council, AYH, undated; Series 5 (Flat box 7, Reel 3)
    The program is listed on the box.
- Ephemera, undated; Series 6; 0.25 Linear Feet
  This series contains patches, a banner, and passbooks from members of AYH. Most items are undated.
  - AYH passes and maps, 1947-1948; Series 6 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - AYH Patches and buttons, undated; Series 6 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - AYH Pennant, undated; Series 6 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Potomac Area Hostels poster, Circa 2000; Series 6 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Banner: 50th, undated; Series 6 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- 2011 donation, 1952-2011; Series 7; 9.25 Linear Feet
  Organized into five subseries: Administrative files, Promotional material, Photographs and negatives, Slides, and Guidebooks.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gift of Donald Messersmith, 2011, 2011.075
  This series contains administrative files, promotional material, photographs, slides, and guidebooks pertaining to American Youth Hostel, Hostelling International, and the Potomac Area Council. The materials in this series date from 1952-2011.
  - Administrative files, circa 1962-2011; Series 7 Subseries 1
    Arranged alphabetically.
    This subseries contains administrative files from various American Youth Hostels. The files include postcards, flyers advertising Washington, D.C. events, Board of Trustees meeting minutes, Potomac Area Council by-laws and policies, etc. The materials in this subseries date from circa 1962-2011.
    - Baltimore Hostel Towson Relations Inc. binder part 1, circa 2001; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Baltimore Hostel Towson Relations Inc. binder part 2, circa 2001; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Board meeting book January-December, 1996; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Board meeting book January-December, 1995; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Board meeting book January-December, 1992; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Board meeting minutes, 1995-2002; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Board meeting minutes, 1998-2001; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Board meeting records biner part 1, 1987-1991; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Board meeting records biner part 2, 1987-1991; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Board meeting records binder part 3, 1987-1991; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Handwritten notebook/records, 1997; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Hostel design blueprints, undated; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Hostelling International annual reports, 1995-1999; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Hostelling International policies, undated; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Loose administrative files, circa 1962-1967; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Loose administrative files, 1965-1966; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Loose administrative files, 1966-1967; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Loose administrative files, 1968-1969; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Loose administrative files, 1970-1972; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Loose administrative files, 1972-1975; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Loose administrative files, 1999-2006; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Operating procedures, undated; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - PAC by-laws, 1983-2002; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - PAC newsletters, 2002-2011; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - PAC office files, 2004-2005; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - PAC September meeting, 2001; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Postcards to Baltimore AYH, 1995; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Washington, D.C. event binder part 1, 1995; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Washington, D.C. event binder part 2, 1995; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Washington, D.C. event binder part 3, 1995; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Washington, D.C. event binder part 1, 1996; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Washington, D.C. event binder part 2, 1996; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Washington, D.C. event binder part 3, 1996; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Washington, D.C. event binder part 1, 1997; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Washington, D.C. event binder part 2, 1997; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Washington, D.C. event binder part 3, 1997; Series 7 Suberies 1 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Promotional material, 1984-1999; Series 7 Subseries 2
    This subseries includes Hostelling International promotional material including one cassette tape, two VHS tapes, slideshow transparencies, and brochures. The materials in this subseries date from 1984-1999.
    - Cassette tape "Hostelling is...", undated; Series 7 Suberies 2 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Hostelling International brochures, undated; Series 7 Suberies 2 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Hostelling International's Guide to Success book, 1992; Series 7 Suberies 2 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Hostelling International slideshow transparencies, undated; Series 7 Suberies 2 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - VHS of news segment featuring Keith Berner of Hostels International, 1999; Series 7 Suberies 2 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - VHS AYH 50th anniversary, 1984; Series 7 Suberies 2 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Photographs and negatives, circa 1985-2005; Series 7 Subseries 3
    This subseries includes photographs and negatives of hostel trips and events. The photos date from circa 1985 to 2005. Photos are generally retained in photo store packets/boxes. The negatives are currently retained alongside their corresponding photographs in the packets/boxes.
    - Miscellaneous photos, circa 1985; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Board retreat, Karma/PATC Pennsylvania, HAP Lincoln, 1988-1989; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - HAP Bear's Den, leadership retreat, International Travel Day, circa 1988; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Miscellanous photos, circa 1988; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous photos, circa 1988; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Baltimore Trip, Harpers Ferry, donors reception, 1988-1989; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Volleyball BBQ, Christmas, Jelleff Homes Baltimore, Halloween, 1988-1989; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - 150 K, X-Party, PIE, 1989; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - 150K Countryside Classic, 1991; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - 150K, loose photos, circa 1992; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - 150 K, volleyball in the fall, loose negatives, 1993; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - AYH Asian DN, Deck the Hostel, 1994; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Larry's bye bye party, AYH 150 K team winners, Halloween, 1994-1995; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - International exchange programs, Cinco de Mayo dinner, 1993-1996; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Volunteer recognition, Larry's going away party, mall volleyball, 150 K, 1994-1995; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - International Travel Day, circa 1995; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - PAC anniversary celebration, 1995; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Volleyball by the bay, 1995; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Volleyball on the Mall, 1995; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Volunteer recognition March 17, volleyball on the mall, 1995-1996; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Volleyball on the Mall, St. Pat's DN, hostel clean-up, 1995-1998; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Halloween party, deck the hostel, Ethiopian dinner, Orioles' game, Russ's farewell, 1996; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - HAP 7/18-8/5, Interntational Travel Day, circa 1996; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - International Travel Day, 1996; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - International Travel Day, 1996-1998; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - International Travel Day, 1997; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - International Travel Day, 1997-1998; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Volleyball by the Bay, Volunteer picnic, Russ's going away, 1996; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - Volleyball on the Mall, deck the hostel, Elizabeth's going away, circa 1996; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - Volleyball on the Mall, open house, Harpers Ferry hostel, circa 1996; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - AYH events, 1997; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Volunteer recognition dinner, Roosevelt High School project, 1998; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Baltimore hostel renovations, 2005; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - International Travel Day, negatives, Easter egg hunt, horseback riding, undated; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Loose, miscellaneous photos, undated; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous photos, undated; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous photos, undated; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Negatives, undated; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - Photos for the AYH display, undated; Series 7 Suberies 3 (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - Slides, circa 1962-2000; Series 7 Subseries 4
    This subseries includes slides of hostel trips and events. The materials in this subseries date from circa 1962-2000. The slides in Box 29 Folder 9 and Box 30 Folders 1 and 2 need to be rehoused into archival sleeves.
    - Baltimore AYH presentation, 1962; Series 7 Subseries 4 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - AYH slides, circa 1980-2000; Series 7 Subseries 4 (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - AYH slides, circa 1980-2000; Series 7 Subseries 4 (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - AYH slides, circa 1980-2000; Series 7 Subseries 4 (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - AYH slides, circa 1980-2000; Series 7 Subseries 4 (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - AYH slides, circa 1980-2000; Series 7 Subseries 4 (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - AYH slides, circa 1980-2000; Series 7 Subseries 4 (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - AYH slides, circa 1980-2000; Series 7 Subseries 4 (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - AYH slides, circa 1987; Series 7 Subseries 4 (Box 28, Folder 9)
    - AYH slides, circa 1987; Series 7 Subseries 4 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - AYH slides, circa 1987; Series 7 Subseries 4 (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - Guidebooks, 1952-2006; Series 7 Subseries 5
    This subseries contains guidebooks and handbooks produced by American Youth Hostels and Hostelling International. The materials date from
    - American Youth Hostel handbooks, 1950-1952; Series 7 Subseries 5 (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - American Youth Hostel handbooks, 1953-1959; Series 7 Subseries 5 (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - American Youth Hostel handbooks, 1963-1969; Series 7 Subseries 5 (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - American Youth Hostel handbooks, 1969-1973; Series 7 Subseries 5 (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - American Youth Hostel handbooks, 1973-1976; Series 7 Subseries 5 (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - American Youth Hostel handbooks, 1977-1980; Series 7 Subseries 5 (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - American Youth Hostel handbooks, 1982-1983; Series 7 Subseries 5 (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - American Youth Hostel handbooks, 1984-1985; Series 7 Subseries 5 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - American Youth Hostel handbooks, 1986-1989; Series 7 Subseries 5 (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - American Youth Hostel handbooks and Hostelling North America, 1990-1991; Series 7 Subseries 5 (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - Hostelling North America handbooks, 1992-1994; Series 7 Subseries 5 (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - Hostelling North America handbooks, 1995-1996; Series 7 Subseries 5 (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - Hostelling International handbooks, 1997-1998; Series 7 Subseries 5 (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Hostelling International handbooks, 1999-2001; Series 7 Subseries 5 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Hostelling International handbooks, 2002-2006; Series 7 Subseries 5 (Box 27, Folder 6)